Camera, Spade and Pen records, 1974-1981
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Camera, Spade and Pen records, 1974-1981
MS 278
Gaede, Marnie
Records, 1974-1980, relating to Camera, Spade, and Pen. Contains chiefly correspondence between the editor, Marnie Gaede, and the contributing authors of the book, Camera, Spade, and Pen, published by The University of Arizona Press in 1980. Also included are drafts of chapters by each author. The supplemental files in the second series relate to the production of the book, and include author releases, the final map of major archaeological sites in the Southwest, an introductory letter to the authors, and biographical perspective information about the book's contributors.
.4 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
In the early 1970s, the husband and wife team of Marc and Marnie Gaede conceived an idea for a book which would approach the subject of Southwestern archaeology in a fresh, new way. Combining their degrees in anthropology with Marc's talent as a photographer and Marnie's skills as a writer and editor, the Gaedes decided to focus the book around Marc's photographs of Southwestern archaeological sites and to include comments about those sites by prominent Southwestern archaeologists who had done field work at those locations.
Organization
This collection is organized into two series:
Series I: Correspondence, 1974-1981
Series II: Supplemental Files, 1974-1980
Scope and Content Note
Records, 1974-1980, relating to Camera, Spade, and Pen. Contains chiefly correspondence between the editor, Marnie Gaede, and the contributing authors of the book, Camera, Spade, and Pen, published by The University of Arizona Press in 1980. Also included are drafts of chapters by each author.
The supplemental files in the second series relate to the production of the book, and include author releases, the final map of major archaeological sites in the Southwest, an introductory letter to the authors, and biographical perspective information about the book's contributors.
Access Terms
Gaede, Marc
Indians of North America -- Southwest, New -- Antiquities
Archaeology -- Southwest, New -- History
Southwest, New -- Antiquities
Correspondence
Container List
- Series I: Correspondence, 1974-1981
  The majority of the correspondence centers around the prospective and the contributing authors to the book and includes letters and manuscripts from J. Richard Ambler, Katharine Bartlett, J.O. Brew, Ned Danson, Jeff Dean, Emil Haury, Julian Hayden, Alden Hayes, Al Lancaster, Bill Lipe. Bob Lister, Don Morris, E.B. Sayles, Watson Smith, R. Gwinn Vivian, and Peter Wray. Also included in the correspondence are letters from prospective publishers, chiefly from the New York Graphic Society.
  Of special interest is a letter from photographer Ansel Adams to the New York Graphic Society recommending that the proposed book, tentatively called Reflections on Southwestern Archaeology, be published. The correspondence also includes decisions by Jesse Nusbaum, Neil Judd, Noel Morss, John B. Rinaldo, Alfred V. Kidder, David A. Breternitz, and Elizabeth Ann Morris not to become contributing authors.
  - Ambler, Dick. 1979 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bartlett, Katharine. 1975-1979 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Brew, J.O. 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Danson, Ned. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Dean, Jeff. 1975-1979 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Haury, Emil. 1974-1980 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Hayden, Julian. 1974-1980 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Hayes, Alden. 1975-1981 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Lancaster, Al. 1974-1976 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Lipe, Bill. 1975-1979 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Lister, Bob. 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Morris, Don. 1975 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Publishers. 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Rejections. 1974-1976 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Sayles, E.B. 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Smith, Watson. 1974-1980 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Vivian, Gwinn. 1976-1979 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Wray, Peter. 1974 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Series II: Supplemental Files, 1974-1980
  The four supplemental files in this series contain material relating to the production of the book, Camera, Spade, and Pen, including author releases from the contributing authors, the final map of Southwestern archaeological sites used in the book, an introductory letter outlining the planned phases of the book, and biographical information about the book's contributors.
  - Author releases. 1974-1980 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Final map. 1974-1980 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Introductory letter to authors. 1974-1980 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Research notes on and biographies by contributors. 1974-1980 (Box 1, Folder 22)